Guide to the Victor W. Von Hagen Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Victor Wolfgang Von Hagen papers
1932-1954
MS 1183
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.5
(4 boxes, 2 folios)
The papers consist of correspondence, research materials, typescripts, and galley proofs for ten books written by Von Hagen relating to Central and South American history.
Von Hagen, Victor Wolfgang, 1908-1985
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Victor W. Von Hagen in 1955.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The main concern of these papers is the writings of Victor W. Von Hagen on South and Central America. The approximately 150 letters (1932-1949) from individuals and institutions deal almost entirely with questions of research and publication of Von Hagen's articles and books. Notable among the correspondents are Sir Charles G. Darwin and Leonard Darwin, relatives of the famous naturalist, Aldous Huxley, Samuel Eliot Morison, and Lewis Mumford. The letters from Mumford, Charles R. Anderson, and Raymond Weaver are of particular interest for the information about Herman Melville which they provide.
Aside from a few financial papers, the remainder of the collection consists of typescripts for six of Von Hagen's books, galley sheets for a seventh, and research materials such as off-prints of articles, transcriptions and photocopies of early letters and other documents from South America, photographs, and notes for various publications. Perhaps most intriguing are the materials relating to The Aztec and Maya Papermakers (published in 1943) which include not only a transcript, galley sheets, extensive research materials, and photographs, but also a large number of samples of paper made from the bark of different types of trees.
Correspondence has been arranged alphabetically by author, writings chronologically by date of publication. A portion of The Aztec and Maya Papermakers materials are located in an oversize box; cross-references are provided in the list of contents on the following page.
These papers were donated to Yale University by Victor W. Von Hagen in 1955.
Biographical / Historical
Author, explorer; expeditions to Mexico, 1931-1933; Ecuador, Upper Amazon, Galapagos Islands, 1934-1936; Honduras, Mosquito Coast, Guatemala, 1937-1938: Northern Panama, 1940; Colombia, Amazon, Peru, 1947-1948; West Indies, 1949-1950; Peru, Bolivia, Ecuador, 1953; director Inca Highway Expedition for American Geographic Society, 1953-1955; dir. Roman roads expedition, North Africa, Jordania, Italy, 1962-1965; author of 48 books.
Aztecs; Indians of North America; Mayas; Miskito Indians; Jicaque Indians; Central America -- History; Galapagos Islands; Latin America -- History; Authors; Von Hagen, Victor Wolfgang, 1908-1985
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, A-W (Box 1, Folder 1 - 10)
  - Writings
    - Introduction to The Encantadas by Herman Melville: notes and research materials, [1940] (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - The Aztec and Maya Papermakers, [1943]
      - Galley sheets (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Proofs of title page and introduction
        General note
        See: Inventory Folder 49
      - Incomplete typescript (Box 1, Folder 13 - 14)
      - Typescript draft (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Samples of bark papers
        See: Inventory Folder 50 - 52
      - Research materials (Box 1, Folder 16 - 17)
        See also: Inventory Folder 53
      - Research materials (photographs) (Box 2, Folder 18)
        See also: Inventory Folder 54
      - Promotional material and review (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - The Jicaque Indians of Honduras, [1943]
      - Typescript (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Research materials (Box 2, Folder 21 - 23)
    - Misikito Boy: research materials, [1943] (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - South America Called Them: research materials, [1943] (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Ecuador and the Galapagos Islands, [1949]
      - Research materials (Box 2, Folder 26 - 28)
      - Research materials (photographs) (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Frederick Catherwood, Architect, [1950] (Box 3)
      - Typescript (Box 3, Folder 30-32)
      - Research materials (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - Research materials (photographs) (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - The Four Seasons of Manuela, [1952]
      - Typescript (Box 3, Folder 35-39)
      - Research materials (Box 4, Folder 40 - 42)
    - Maya Explorer: research materials, [1954] (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Death on the Galapagos: typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 44 - 45)
    - Smugglers to the South: typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Miscellaneous notes and research materials, 1933-38, undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Financial papers, 1950-51 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Oversize materials (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Oversize materials (Box 5, Folder 50 - 52)
  - Oversize materials (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Oversize materials (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - The Aztec and Maya Papermakers, 1943 (Box 6)